<rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" version="2.0"><channel><title>Gaurav Chandrashekar (Gou-rave)</title><description>Entrepreneur, Software Developer, Product Guy, Javascript, Skydiver, Freediver, Swimrunner, Tablist, What's worth solving?</description><link>http://localhost:2368/</link><generator>Ghost 0.11</generator><lastBuildDate>Wed, 23 May 2018 00:11:57 GMT</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://localhost:2368/rss/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><ttl>60</ttl><item><title>Skydiving</title><description>&lt;p&gt;I spent the last three weeks learning how to sky dive and got my A license, a ticket for me to jump out of planes around the world - and loved it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://d.cggaurav.net/jkAnzt/5cIBhrPi+" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A shout out to the amazing instructors at Skydance Skydiving in Davis, California; and the incredible community of&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>http://localhost:2368/2017/08/08/skydiving/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">18442198-6cbb-40f7-a490-c8c8ac749d71</guid><dc:creator>Gaurav C</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 08 Aug 2017 23:29:17 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;I spent the last three weeks learning how to sky dive and got my A license, a ticket for me to jump out of planes around the world - and loved it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://d.cggaurav.net/jkAnzt/5cIBhrPi+" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A shout out to the amazing instructors at Skydance Skydiving in Davis, California; and the incredible community of wingsuiters, base jumpers and other recreational jumpers I got to jump with in my ~30 jumps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These were a few lessons I took away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;That fear is only in the mind. The possibility of you dropping into the floor dead is highly unlikely. Often thoughts about “if this then what”, mostly all hypotheticals, start popping up and affecting my present state of mind.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you go after fear enough number of times, it goes away. I did not feel that much fear after dive 15 and exits were more fun! It did come back a little when I had to pack my own parachute. ;)  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The point of maximum fear is the point of minimum danger. Your mind plays games with you.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The first dive, even though I had prepared well, I took more time to get started. But you can only meditate so much, only prepare so much. At one point that I could be more aware of - you just act and trust your guts.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;On that note, one my main learnings from the instructors, different ones at different points is to think less, feel more. I was being too analytical about safety, a lot of questions (ain’t bad) but to enjoy the jump, you have to let go and feel more.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Often when you become fearless, you become complacent and thats when mistakes start kicking in.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;That you could be in more control than you think you are. And the feeling of complete control over your actions is liberating.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You have to work for your dive - I have a new found respect for packing parachutes and further, thinking of it as an art. Its also fruit for the hard work.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A lot of work is before the actual jump. Its the preparation behind the scenes, the things that you can’t see, the intangibles.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sky diving is not for the crazy, its for the folks who can deal with calculated risk, perhaps even take advantage of it.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The more the fear, the more the thrill. That’s the way to look at it.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Everytime I go up, I am amazed what humanity has achieved. Farms, roads, other planes, small cars that I can see, an actual plane that you are in that you can jump out of, etc.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Packing such a big parachute into such a small bag has given me packing super powers. I used to dread packing my bags before traveling, but now its a challenge and I found my last pack to be super easy. Could fit in 20% more to my surprise.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fun is best when shared. The solo dives used to get boring after my jump 20, but its super fun when you jump with other people and do crazy maneuvers.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In freefall, I felt a lightness, a strong presence, a calm and a right here, right now feeling that I hope to be in more of in normal life.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The last 6 weeks in preparation was also a practice in not drinking alcohol, being disciplined and committed about getting everyday right and going back into the drop zone with the excitement and fear you had on day one.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Even if the freefall is less than 80 seconds, time slows down. It actually feels much slower and you are aware of every small moment. Its beautiful.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;As Josh, the main rigger put it, we are not supposed to have this much fun as men. That’s skydiving. ;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here goes one of my favorite jumps, learning how to stabilize in the air.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/_8B7z5mf6Kw" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>High Altitude Mountaineering 101</title><description>&lt;p&gt;Having spent three months in Quito at 2.8K m above sea level, I got intrigued about climbing high altitude mountains, above 4K m. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first week, I climbed Pinchincha, 10 miles from Quito at 4.97K m and realized how difficult it was. Even though you could be fit&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>http://localhost:2368/2017/03/21/high-altitude-mountaineering-101/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">55e5b2e6-f5e5-44b5-8282-965e27d56bd7</guid><dc:creator>Gaurav C</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 21 Mar 2017 18:05:21 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Having spent three months in Quito at 2.8K m above sea level, I got intrigued about climbing high altitude mountains, above 4K m. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first week, I climbed Pinchincha, 10 miles from Quito at 4.97K m and realized how difficult it was. Even though you could be fit physically, your mind needs to adapt well to handle low oxygen, so your mind keeps telling you to stop and return. Further, the biggest lesson from climbing a mountain is that getting to the top is only 40% of the trouble and most of the known accidents happen while on descent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mountain climbing is an experiment in mindfulness where you  have to take deep slow breaths and just focus on the next step upward or downward. I realized that its important to keep moving, even if they are slow steps instead of stopping; stopping makes you feel restful and your mind goes back to saying its time to get back; Restarts become harder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Respect the mountain; its the journey of climbing up and respect comes in the forms of accepting you cannot go all the way to the peak if the weather is against you.  Its not just about getting up to the peak but enjoying the climb and nature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One needs strong glutes, hamstring and quads and running at high altitude prepares your lungs. Climb acclimiting mountains first before going for higher mountains.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Equipment  - keep luggage as low as possible &lt;br&gt;
1. Helmet with a compartment for lights if you are well into the night. &lt;br&gt;
2. Ice axe - for both in ice,snow &amp;amp; sand,rocks. &lt;br&gt;
3. Fleece jackets - Inner layers to keep as warm as possible. &lt;br&gt;
4. Crampons - A layer below your shoes for the grip in ice. &lt;br&gt;
5. Gaiters - the socks that hold your show up and covers your pants from getting wet &lt;br&gt;
6. Water bottle - Plastic bottle freezes &lt;br&gt;
7. The thickest socks you can find. &lt;br&gt;
8. Food&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Generally digestion is affected at high altitude and you feel gaseous. Cocao tea leaves help - energy and digestion.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Not too much sugary chocolate as getting a sugar high doensn’t help. Raisins help.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don’t use any altitude sickness pills. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hydrate, hydrate, hydrate.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Apply sunscreen before the climb. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pushing yourself too much and going too hard at high altitude can make you dizzy and can be dangerous in rough and steep terrain where you need to keep your wits about on where to place your hands and feet, check for loose rocks etc. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://d.cggaurav.net/Jgyi/4Df65uaw+" alt="Climbing Cayambe ~5K m"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://d.cggaurav.net/1eO7f/21IGNTlz+" alt="Illiniza Norte at 5.3K m"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>On Ecuador: Working, the Andes and the Galapagos</title><description>&lt;p&gt;I spent three months in Quito, Ecuador and it was my first time in Latin America. I loved it and these are a bunch of things I noted down randomly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Quito is 2.8K m above sea level and the high altitude hits you. I felt very sleepy the first&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;</description><link>http://localhost:2368/2017/03/21/on-ecuador-working-the-andes-and-galapagos/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">b426eb0a-1c23-43e5-8c39-a9f9e2696134</guid><dc:creator>Gaurav C</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 21 Mar 2017 17:41:56 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;I spent three months in Quito, Ecuador and it was my first time in Latin America. I loved it and these are a bunch of things I noted down randomly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Quito is 2.8K m above sea level and the high altitude hits you. I felt very sleepy the first two days but then got accustomed to it after I went for a couple of morning runs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ecuador is a great place to learn Spanish since they do not have an accent like other Latin American countries. I did an hour of class every weekday and loved the teachers at &lt;a href="http://www.simon-bolivar.com/"&gt;Simon Bolivar&lt;/a&gt; School. I continue to learn from them online.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Most Latin American metropolitan cities have something called the Cycle Pass, [Cyclo Paseo] or &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ciclopaseo_in_Quito"&gt;Cyclovia&lt;/a&gt; where they cordon off major roads on Sunday for runners, skateboarders and bicyclists.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Oh, there are no lights for pedestrians. Cross the roads at your own risk.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;After Cotopaxi erupted early 2016 and a recovering economy after switching to US dollars, the country is growing and still underrated in Latin America.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ecuador is known for the Highlands(Andes), Coast(Montanita), Amazonas far east and the Galapagos!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Quito is on the Equator, the sun is up at 6 am sharp, and people rise early, sleep early.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I found it surprising the way you greet women by bumping cheeks, but not women.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Park Carolina in Quito is like the Central Park of New York.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The startup ecosystem is still nascent, and young smart folks are working on interesting problems at &lt;a href="http://www.buentriphub.com/"&gt;Buen Trip Hub&lt;/a&gt;, where I spent my day time working. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I got interested in high altitude mountain climbing (on another post) after climbing Pichincha, Illiniza Norte and Cayambe!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;On Food
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;I loved the almuerzo/lunch. Looked forward to it everyday; includes jugo/juice - and the kinds of fruits you see are exotic - probably never heard of them(Maracuya, Granadilla, &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://es.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cebiche_de_chochos"&gt;Chocho&lt;/a&gt; was a high protien corn that I used to have for breakfasts.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Guayusa is a tea made of cocaine leaves (like hoja de coca), great for high altitude and replaces the high you need from coffee.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://localhost:2368/2017/03/21/on-ecuador-working-the-andes-and-galapagos/"&gt;Canelazo&lt;/a&gt; is a drink made from cinnonen and local liquor, served hot and available at any street shop. Gives you a sugar high.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.tuenti.ec"&gt;Tuenti&lt;/a&gt; has a great connectivity for a SIM card, though you need a local friend for you to get it activated.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Expressways all across Ecuador is well planned and laid out. The professional cyclists come from all across the world to bike here to improve their lung capacity.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Uber does not work in Ecuador yet, Cabify came to my rescue.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;On Galapagos
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;One of the most beautiful islands I have been to; the animals have grown away from human contact and come so close. &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=gTjgDY9bQvc"&gt;Sharks&lt;/a&gt;, Turtles, Sea lions, Iguanas - you will need at least two weeks for Santa Cruz, Isabella and San Cristobal.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I hit me knee during snorkeling and had free emergency care, X-ray and consultation, which is was exceptionally surprising.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I'll leave this here. &lt;img src="http://d.cggaurav.net/Z3c4/2gQjq125+" alt="" title=""&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, the people are really nice, gave me a comfortable environment for getting good work done and I am going back to Ecuador to climb Chimborazo and Cayambe :)&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Being more mindful and less distracted using technology</title><description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Technology promised us productivity and delivered on that promise, but didn’t tell us the cost would be our sanity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tech through digital devices which we use when we are at home, at work or mobile have made us incredibly productive, connecting us to people around the world, bringing information&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>http://localhost:2368/2016/11/23/being-more-mindful-and-less-distracted-using-technology/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">7b5ade6b-7eaa-48fa-b5f9-4c6024a68e2a</guid><dc:creator>Gaurav C</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 23 Nov 2016 22:30:38 GMT</pubDate><media:content url="http://localhost:2368/content/images/2016/11/1-WOQOpwAvA54ZyLuvGa5LrQ.jpeg" medium="image"/><content:encoded>&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;img src="http://localhost:2368/content/images/2016/11/1-WOQOpwAvA54ZyLuvGa5LrQ.jpeg" alt="Being more mindful and less distracted using technology"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Technology promised us productivity and delivered on that promise, but didn’t tell us the cost would be our sanity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tech through digital devices which we use when we are at home, at work or mobile have made us incredibly productive, connecting us to people around the world, bringing information at our finger tips and bridging inequality. We have and continue to be benefitted with positive impacts of technology that we fail to recognize how much better it can be. &lt;br&gt;
Here are tools you can use to be more effective, mindful, less distracted more proactive and less reactive using your digital devices that I have found to be useful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id="caveats"&gt;Caveats&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;a) This is not about valuing productivity or technology tools over purpose. &lt;br&gt;
b) Not every tool might be useful or be on your platform. &lt;br&gt;
c) Yes, technology is a tool and its how we use it. However, we don’t have infinite will power to be always in control and this article is to have a few constraints in place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Chrome Apps&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1. &lt;a href="https://medium.com/r/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fmomentumdash.com%2F"&gt;Momentum Dash&lt;/a&gt; for a lovely Chrome homepage with a photo from around the world and which asks you ‘What is your focus for today?’ &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2. &lt;a href="https://medium.com/r/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fchrome.google.com%2Fwebstore%2Fdetail%2Fxtab%2Famddgdnlkmohapieeekfknakgdnpbleb"&gt;xTab&lt;/a&gt; for limiting the number of tabs you have to Chrome. I suggest &amp;lt;10. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3. &lt;a href="https://medium.com/r/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fchrome.google.com%2Fwebstore%2Fdetail%2Fpapier%2Fhhjeaokafplhjoogdemakihhdhffacia"&gt;Papier&lt;/a&gt; for having a lovely static note as your homepage to remind you of what is important &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;4. &lt;a href="https://medium.com/r/?url=http%3A%2F%2Fcount.life%2F"&gt;Count.Life&lt;/a&gt; if you need some pressure to get stuff done. It visually tells you how much more you have to live. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;5. &lt;a href="https://medium.com/r/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fchrome.google.com%2Fwebstore%2Fdetail%2Fnews-feed-eradicator-for%2Ffjcldmjmjhkklehbacihaiopjklihlgg"&gt;Facebook News Feed Eradicator&lt;/a&gt; to remove your Facebook News Feed with quotes, with custom ones. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mac&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1. Keep your Dock on auto hide so notifications don’t interrupt you. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2. &lt;a href="https://medium.com/r/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fmanytricks.com%2Fmoom%2F"&gt;Moom&lt;/a&gt; to help you resize windows so you can keep them in fullscreen. &lt;a href="https://medium.com/r/?url=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.irradiatedsoftware.com%2Fsizeup%2F"&gt;Sizeup&lt;/a&gt; is an alternative. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3. &lt;a href="https://medium.com/r/?url=http%3A%2F%2Flightheadsw.com%2Fcaffeine%2F"&gt;Caffeine&lt;/a&gt; to keep your Mac alive so if you go for a coffee break, a login doesn’t distract you. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;4. &lt;a href="https://medium.com/r/?url=http%3A%2F%2Fselfcontrolapp.com%2F"&gt;Self Control&lt;/a&gt;, my favorite app, free that lets you block out distracting sites that you list for a set number of hours. Even restarts won’t let you open them. &lt;a href="https://medium.com/r/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fheyfocus.com%2F"&gt;Heyfocus&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a href="https://medium.com/r/?url=https%3A%2F%2Ffreedom.to%2F"&gt;Freedom&lt;/a&gt; are alternatives. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;5. &lt;a href="https://medium.com/r/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fjustgetflux.com%2F"&gt;Flux&lt;/a&gt; reduces blue light in the evening and dims your screen to not affect your sleep! &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;6. &lt;a href="https://medium.com/r/?url=http%3A%2F%2Falternoteapp.com%2F"&gt;Alternote&lt;/a&gt; as a distraction free alternative to Evernote. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;7. Ambient Noise has said to improve productivity. I use &lt;a href="https://medium.com/r/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.focusatwill.com%2Fapp%2FsignIn%2Fform"&gt;Noisli&lt;/a&gt;; &lt;a href="https://medium.com/r/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcoffitivity.com%2F%23research"&gt;Coffivity&lt;/a&gt; is great and mimics the background noise in a coffee shop. &lt;a href="https://medium.com/r/?url=http%3A%2F%2Ffocusatwill.com"&gt;FocusAtWill&lt;/a&gt; is a known alternative. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;8. &lt;a href="https://medium.com/r/?url=http%3A%2F%2Fbreaktimeapp.com%2F"&gt;Breaktime&lt;/a&gt; forces you to take a break after a set number of hours, even if it is for 10 seconds. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;9. &lt;a href="https://medium.com/r/?url=http%3A%2F%2Frescuetime.com"&gt;RescueTime&lt;/a&gt; for tracking which apps you use on your Mac and you get a Productivity score via email every week. Recommended. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;10. &lt;a href="https://medium.com/r/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fget.slack.help%2Fhc%2Fen-us%2Farticles%2F214908388-Do-Not-Disturb-and-snooze-settings"&gt;Slack DND&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;11. If you use Soundcloud via the browser, &lt;a href="https://medium.com/r/?url=http%3A%2F%2Fsoundcleod.com"&gt;SoundCleod&lt;/a&gt; is useful. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;12. Use &lt;a href="https://medium.com/r/?url=http%3A%2F%2Fmessenger.com"&gt;messenger.com&lt;/a&gt; or better a &lt;a href="https://medium.com/r/?url=https%3A%2F%2Ffbmacmessenger.rsms.me%2F"&gt;Messenger app&lt;/a&gt; instead of facebook.com. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;13. Use the &lt;a href="https://medium.com/r/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fblog.whatsapp.com%2F10000621%2FIntroducing-WhatsApps-desktop-app"&gt;desktop Whatsapp&lt;/a&gt; app instead of on the browser or even your phone. 14. Next time you unlock your Mac, be aware of your posture and sit comfortably. #challenge &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Email&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1600/1*Ozftw-9p9EqWdA4xx-nJ9w.jpeg" alt="Being more mindful and less distracted using technology"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;figcaption class="imageCaption" contenteditable="true" data-default-value="Type caption for image (optional)"&gt;Remember you pulling to refresh 10 seconds just after you did to see that you have no email again?&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Research: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;a) &lt;a href="https://medium.com/r/?url=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.huffingtonpost.com%2Flinda-stone%2Fjust-breathe-building-the_b_85651.html"&gt;Email apnea&lt;/a&gt; is where you have shallow breathing, a hold of your breath when you open to email. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;b) &lt;a href="https://medium.com/r/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fen.wikipedia.org%2Fwiki%2FContinuous_partial_attention"&gt;Continuous Partial Attention&lt;/a&gt;: With our digital devices, we are always open to interruptions and have our attention divided on multiple contexts/tasks at the same time. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1. Email has been said to cause &lt;a href="https://medium.com/r/?url=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.telegraph.co.uk%2Fnews%2F2016%2F03%2F22%2Fpsychologists-warn-constant-email-notifications-are-toxic-source%2F"&gt;stress&lt;/a&gt; and sudden changes of emotion. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2. Have email curfew: Set a few hours and times a day to access email. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3. &lt;a href="https://medium.com/r/?url=http%3A%2F%2Finbox.google.com"&gt;Inbox&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://medium.com/r/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcloudmagic.com%2Fk%2Fnewton"&gt;Newton&lt;/a&gt; are great examples to make email easier for you though we are not there yet. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Phone&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1. Update your notifications. Notifications is the single point of entry where you get distracted. Have notifications from people, not apps. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2. Use QualityTime to be aware of how you use your phone. Android only.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1600/1*w8HfDUiAjUc2xAUpj1_0vA.png" alt="Being more mindful and less distracted using technology"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1. Home screen: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;a) Have just a home screen and a secondary screen, nothing more. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;b) Choose your home screen to have the most useful, utility based apps. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2. Prefer not having FB or Instagram installed. Instead use them on your browser. By giving yourself a bad experience on the browser, you tend to use it lesser and more effectively. Alternatively, use just the &lt;a href="https://medium.com/r/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.messenger.com"&gt;Messenger&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://medium.com/r/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fgroups.fb.com%2F"&gt;Facebook Groups&lt;/a&gt; app. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3. Voice: Use apps like &lt;a href="https://medium.com/r/?url=https%3A%2F%2Frogertalk.com%2Fabout"&gt;Roger&lt;/a&gt; to not text while driving and also say things like “I’ll be there in 10 minutes” more effectively. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;4. Keyboards: Use &lt;a href="https://medium.com/r/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fswiftkey.com%2Fen"&gt;SwiftKey&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href="https://medium.com/r/?url=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.swype.com%2F"&gt;Swype&lt;/a&gt; to type faster and easier. I use Swiftkey to learn new languages as it helps you auto suggest the next world. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;5. Keep the colorful apps that ask for your attention grouped into a a box so its less likely you are going to react to it. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;6. Sleep: a) Charge your phone away from your bed :) #challenge b) Give yourself time to boot up when you wake up instead of checking your phone. #challenge &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;7. While being out for dinner or lunch, keep your phone faced down. Its less likely you are going to have deep conversations as research shows that we are open to being interrupted with the phone faced upwards. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;8. Make your screen grayscale, its proven to be less distracting because bright colors subconsciously attract your attention and emotions are correlated with color perception. &lt;a href="https://medium.com/r/?url=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.tech-recipes.com%2Frx%2F50275%2Fhow-do-i-turn-my-iphones-screen-mode-to-grayscale%2F"&gt;iPhone&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://medium.com/r/?url=http%3A%2F%2Fandroid.stackexchange.com%2Fquestions%2F74887%2Fforce-android-to-display-in-grayscale"&gt;Android&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Meditation&lt;/strong&gt; If you are into meditation, these three apps are great &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1. &lt;a href="https://medium.com/r/?url=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.donothingfor2minutes.com%2F"&gt;DoNothingForTwoMinutes&lt;/a&gt;: I can never finish this #challenge! &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2. &lt;a href="https://medium.com/r/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.headspace.com%2F"&gt;Headspace&lt;/a&gt;: for those getting into meditation &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3. &lt;a href="https://medium.com/r/?url=https%3A%2F%2Finsighttimer.com%2F"&gt;Insight Timer&lt;/a&gt;: to give you a community to meditate with and a vide variety of meditations &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;4. &lt;a href="https://medium.com/r/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.calm.com%2F"&gt;Calm.com&lt;/a&gt; peaceful meditative sessions not more than 15 minutes long, you can use it even in your commute. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks to &lt;a href="https://medium.com/u/c806a873d503"&gt;Tristan Harris&lt;/a&gt; for inspiration, here you can find the s&lt;a href="https://medium.com/r/?url=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.slideshare.net%2FGauravChandrashekar%2Fmore-effective-using-technology"&gt;lides from talk at Dojo Bali &lt;/a&gt;. In closing,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1600/1*UQyE7lidpYRxtV5dRruGug.jpeg" alt="Being more mindful and less distracted using technology"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cross posted on &lt;a href="https://calmingdesign.co/how-to-be-more-mindful-and-less-distracted-using-technology-f8fdf7d36fe5#.fqfnpir1s"&gt;Medium&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Freediving</title><description>&lt;h5 id="notesfromfreediving101"&gt;Notes from Free diving 101&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I went for a basic free diving course in Tulamben, Bali and these were the quick notes from the three days of intensive diving.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?feature=player_embedded&amp;amp;v=KaW_58jlkE4 &lt;br /&gt;
" target="_blank"&gt;&lt;img src="http://img.youtube.com/vi/KaW_58jlkE4/1.jpg" alt="" width="480" height="360" border="10"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id="twosectionbreathing"&gt;Two section breathing&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;a) Fill the base of your stomach first &lt;br&gt;
b) Then go after the lungs&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Have normal breaths or&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>http://localhost:2368/2016/11/05/freediving/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">b8a6afff-ca2a-496b-90be-9b6231b9a7a0</guid><dc:creator>Gaurav C</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 05 Nov 2016 06:53:10 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;h5 id="notesfromfreediving101"&gt;Notes from Free diving 101&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I went for a basic free diving course in Tulamben, Bali and these were the quick notes from the three days of intensive diving.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?feature=player_embedded&amp;amp;v=KaW_58jlkE4 &lt;br /&gt;
" target="_blank"&gt;&lt;img src="http://img.youtube.com/vi/KaW_58jlkE4/1.jpg" alt="" width="480" height="360" border="10"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id="twosectionbreathing"&gt;Two section breathing&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;a) Fill the base of your stomach first &lt;br&gt;
b) Then go after the lungs&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Have normal breaths or flashes to compensate for the lack of oxygen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id="twotypesoffreediving"&gt;Two types of Freediving&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;a) Free immersion - you go with the line &lt;br&gt;
b) Constant weight- you go with the flippers&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Keep equalising and specifically for me - I need to equalise more in the first few meters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Keep your self relaxed. Your body is asking you to breathe, but if you keep your muscles relaxed and mind calm you last longer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Its good to take your time and relax yourself before you go in. No rush and no need to talk. Just focus on your self. Close your eyes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Never exhale before reaching the surface, you need the air for equalization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id="equalization"&gt;Equalization&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Valsalva - Force air from the lungs, natural. Takes more energy  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Frenzel - No effort from diaphragm &lt;br&gt;
Push air with the back of tongue against palette. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?feature=player_embedded&amp;amp;v=rUOR6KZ3-RI &lt;br /&gt;
" target="_blank"&gt;&lt;img src="http://img.youtube.com/vi/rUOR6KZ3-RI/0.jpg" alt="IMAGE ALT TEXT HERE" width="240" height="180" border="10"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Safety mechanisms &lt;br&gt;
For Blackout, BTT - Blow, Tap, Talk &lt;br&gt;
Go and wait at around 10m for the fellow diver to come&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id="mylessons"&gt;My lessons&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mind over matter&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t hyperventilate. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you think you are going to panic, take a second, observe and relax. Its like meditation. &lt;br&gt;
Its not about going deeper, its about getting the technique right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id="pranayama"&gt;Pranayama&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Kapalabhathi - Skull breathing  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Samavritti - Square breathing, 6.6.6.6  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Uddiyana Bandha - To help the movement for the diaphragm &lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=l2R0dkzkbzE"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?feature=player_embedded&amp;amp;v=l2R0dkzkbzE &lt;br /&gt;
" target="_blank"&gt;&lt;img src="http://img.youtube.com/vi/l2R0dkzkbzE/0.jpg" alt="" width="240" height="180" border="10"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Course PDF: &lt;a href="http://d.cggaurav.net/FZ6B"&gt;http://d.cggaurav.net/FZ6B&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>On Vipassana</title><description>&lt;p&gt;I just spent 10 days in a Vipassana near Ubud in Landih Ashram, which is amidst the mountains near the Kintamani Agung, mountiain that’s around 2000m high, the weather is around 25*C, rains mildly, bust most of all you are amidst beautiful nature. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We had an international group&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>http://localhost:2368/2016/11/05/on-vipassana/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">51f210d9-2dab-4fb1-a82a-122b771aa915</guid><dc:creator>Gaurav C</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 05 Nov 2016 06:49:57 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;I just spent 10 days in a Vipassana near Ubud in Landih Ashram, which is amidst the mountains near the Kintamani Agung, mountiain that’s around 2000m high, the weather is around 25*C, rains mildly, bust most of all you are amidst beautiful nature. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We had an international group of students from all over the world and the teachers flew in all the way from Canada to teach the course. Note that all of Vipassana runs on donations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://d.cggaurav.net/GrRb+" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id="whatisvipassana"&gt;What is Vipassana?&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Pali, the language that Buddha spoke 2500 years ago, it means looking at reality as is and not who you want it to be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I went in with an open mind and took it up as a challenge to meditate straight for 10 days which I have never done before. I have done meditations before and come from a culture where I have meditated from young. Further, I have never been away from using my phone or computer for that long either.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id="howdoesitwork"&gt;How does it work?&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In general you are meditating close to 7 hours starting at 4 am and ending at 9 pm with 4 sessions, spread across 2 hour and 1 hour sessions with a discourse for an hour with Goenka at 7:30 pm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id="thoughts"&gt;Thoughts&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No, you don’t get enlightened in 10 days.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I became more aware of the reactive nature of my mind.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When fear or anxiety arises in any thought  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;At some points, I went on a journey with an idea 5. I had in mind, and gave power to the thought and loved the journey, though that’s craving and the process is to be aware of the imagination and get back to the present moment.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Some thoughts get crazy when you do nothing but meditate. Movies, comics and nightmares, dreams don’t even define crazy. An idle mind is a devils’ workshop and that’s what you learn about the mind.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Self doubt crept in whether if I am doing this right and I did think about skipping sessions, slept through a few and did want to leave on the 6th day. But the teacher was kind and prodded me further.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You become very aware of bodily sensations even at the tiniest parts.This is the core of Vipassana to know what you feel to any stimuli with your body and short circuit if and how your mind reacts to it. Your mind has a lot of preconditioning on how to react to fear, anxiety, pain, love, happiness etc.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Disassociate physical pain from mental pain. &lt;br&gt;
I faced a lot of back pain from the 4th day and interestingly on the 7th, once you don’t react to the pain and you focus your attention on different parts of the body, you only sense the physical pain and that’s bearable. :)  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I ended up just smiling for no reason the the whole of last day.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You deeply understand and experience your reality, the sensations that you have in your body, moment to moment.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Irrespective of what you feel or think, you maintain equanimity and awareness moment to moment, with non reactivity, not having aversion fo the pain to go or having craving for any kind of sensations.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Vipassana is more practical than I thought it was. Leave philosophy and intellectual discussions aside and dives deep in.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You tend to observe even the tiniest detail of sound, light, sight in nature and start observing things in detail in your breaks, which is beautiful  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You are agitated initially for a couple of days wondering what’s happening on FB, Instagram, if you’ll miss a major event in the world, but life goes on and on the 11th day I was overwhelmed opening my phone again. I am more aware now, at least briefly since its just two days how I am using my devices.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I felt like continuing further after 10 days in the state of silence and work deeper in my meditations.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Starting to talk again on the 10th day feels awkward, and puts your brain in another mode altogether, the ‘chattering’ mode and is the day to day modality of the brain, not what you experience at Vipassana! You do feel like a child again talking. My words weighed more the last few days, lets see!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For friends who are interested in trying Vipassana &lt;br&gt;
If you are new to meditation, I suggest taking a few weeks before to meditate and feel comfortable meditating an hour everyday. &lt;br&gt;
Be mentally prepared that its not a retreat where you relax. You need to work on your meditation. &lt;br&gt;
Be physically fit, and have your back and glutes strong. You’ll have to sit for a long hours being still. &lt;br&gt;
Take as many cushions as you need to make you feel comfortable during meditations. &lt;br&gt;
Have a sweater to feel warm during the night if its cold in your location.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>On Remote Working and being a Digital Nomad</title><description>&lt;h6 id="whydigitalnomadremoteworkinglifestyle"&gt;Why Digital Nomad/Remote Working Lifestyle?&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How people work is changing and with advancing technology, location is becoming less important. People are looking at alternative lifestyles, challenging status quo to work better and redefine what it is to have a good life.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Travel the world, learn new things and experience&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;</description><link>http://localhost:2368/2016/09/23/on-remote-working-and-being-a-digital-nomad/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">6dc390d8-77e9-44ee-9b4c-5f125e357b19</guid><dc:creator>Gaurav C</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 23 Sep 2016 06:47:14 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;h6 id="whydigitalnomadremoteworkinglifestyle"&gt;Why Digital Nomad/Remote Working Lifestyle?&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How people work is changing and with advancing technology, location is becoming less important. People are looking at alternative lifestyles, challenging status quo to work better and redefine what it is to have a good life.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Travel the world, learn new things and experience new cultures. I am amazed that people have such different lifestyles once you get out of the 9 - 5 routine.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Independence and freedom to live where ever you please.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Good quality of life and great savings, because of global arbitrage.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Augment immigration and work laws of different countries.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Great collaboration tools and they can only get better. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h6 id="whynotdigitalnomadremoteworkinglifestyle"&gt;Why not Digital Nomad/Remote Working Lifestyle?&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You don't have your coworkers next to you and associated concerns with being in sync with the vision, product and ideas discussed day to day.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;"Out of sight, out of mind" that you need to accept and proactively work with communicating transparently, effectively and constantly  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you don't have the discipline to set work hours and stick to you it, its easy to fall into a holiday mood.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Close friends and relationships take a hit. Most people you meet are there where you are only for a short term. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That being said, there are successful companies like Github, Buffer, Baremetrics, StackOverflow, 37 Signals that thrive being remote and its just the beginning to see how the culture scales in a decade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id="whatihaveseentoworkbetterbeingremote"&gt;What I have seen to work better being remote.&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Get a coworking space. Don’t work from home. Create your own office. Coffee places are good -  you can guarantee a good connection. The advantage of the coworking space is the community of potentially remote workers that you can connect with.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Take notes on all video calls,meetings and ideally email it to the team as a summary everyday or just for yourself so you know what you worked on. Its a daily summary of what you worked on. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Set the hours and days you want to work for the week beforehand and let your team know. Show yourself. Sync this with at least 4 hour everyday where the team all works together.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you can’t meet a deadline, let the team know in advance. Way in advance if you are remote. Shit happens.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Often talk to your team about the challenges of being remote and how it can be solved. Ask the team to write things down in chat or any other medium to keep things noted down and async.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Tools&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Slack for day to day questions and discussions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Github for code and PR reviews&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Trello for threaded long term conversations on features&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I use Droplr for sharing screenshots&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Give yourself the time for ad hoc meetings. Be online, ping your team members for a quick 10 minute call. Let them to be open for it too. This is the digital alternative to going to your coworkers desk.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I still think remote work works best if the immediate team you are working with is small, &amp;lt; 7 members. I also think being a developer remotely has specific advantages aligned for being remote. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Keep all communication transparent and threaded. Start talking, typing more :)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://d.cggaurav.net/48Ex+"&gt;Say Good morning&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It takes a couple of weeks to feel comfortable but you'll get there :)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Scuba Diving 101</title><description>&lt;p&gt;Scuba Diving at the Libery Ship Wreck in Tulamben Bali as I take on a challenge and go on a night dive too!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src="https://drive.google.com/embeddedfolderview?id=0B9GBVf4V05ShSFZlYVpEdFJoSmc#grid" width="100%" height="500" frameborder="0"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;</description><link>http://localhost:2368/2016/08/22/scuba-diving/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">065ed3f8-3f68-4b5c-9bec-c66ffbe2aed2</guid><dc:creator>Gaurav C</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 22 Aug 2016 17:43:05 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Scuba Diving at the Libery Ship Wreck in Tulamben Bali as I take on a challenge and go on a night dive too!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src="https://drive.google.com/embeddedfolderview?id=0B9GBVf4V05ShSFZlYVpEdFJoSmc#grid" width="100%" height="500" frameborder="0"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>GOQii</title><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://goqii.com"&gt;GOQii&lt;/a&gt; is a growing global company, started by serial entrepreneur, &lt;a href="http://twitter.com/vishalgondal"&gt;Vishal Gondal&lt;/a&gt;, that provides motivation for being healthier and fitter by matching you with fitness coaches around the world. Even though FitBit and wearables market grew exponentially the last 5 years, what they didn't solve is actually making people healthier&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>http://localhost:2368/2015/11/05/goqii/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">02b57074-f1c8-41c6-a6f9-50f236ba8c90</guid><dc:creator>Gaurav C</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 05 Nov 2015 07:12:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://goqii.com"&gt;GOQii&lt;/a&gt; is a growing global company, started by serial entrepreneur, &lt;a href="http://twitter.com/vishalgondal"&gt;Vishal Gondal&lt;/a&gt;, that provides motivation for being healthier and fitter by matching you with fitness coaches around the world. Even though FitBit and wearables market grew exponentially the last 5 years, what they didn't solve is actually making people healthier since motivation was missing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From May to August 2015, working with developers and designers out of Bangalore, as a product owner, I help increase ratings on the Android store from 2 to 3.5 and redesigned chat, profile and dashboard for both platforms. These designs show case some of the work done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://d.cggaurav.net/69eq+" alt=""&gt;
&lt;img src="http://d.cggaurav.net/NIz7+" alt=""&gt;
&lt;img src="http://d.cggaurav.net/IBEW+" alt=""&gt;
&lt;img src="http://d.cggaurav.net/Bzdd+" alt=""&gt;
&lt;img src="http://d.cggaurav.net/iNbr+" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://d.cggaurav.net/XDuO+" alt="Style Guide"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Spotify AlbumArt</title><description>&lt;p&gt;Visualizing an Artist Album Art&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The content/images that turn out as album art are creative and as a small hack, I spent some time looking at how you can get an artist top albums' art into a single unified view. With Spotify not having an open API to pull&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>http://localhost:2368/2014/01/07/spotify-albumart-2/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">114d93d3-bb9b-4b5d-b884-c80c7b4ce68e</guid><category>Spotify</category><category>albumArt</category><dc:creator>Gaurav C</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2014 21:22:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Visualizing an Artist Album Art&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The content/images that turn out as album art are creative and as a small hack, I spent some time looking at how you can get an artist top albums' art into a single unified view. With Spotify not having an open API to pull album art, I had to look up an &lt;a href="https://embed.spotify.com/oembed/?url=http://open.spotify.com/track/6JoxpsF0yzjRcZyrPJPfXY"&gt;unofficial albumArt API&lt;/a&gt; to pull the album Art in different sizes. Further, with a dirty CSS background-image hack, you can visualize the artwork at &lt;a href="http://cggaurav.github.io/albumart/"&gt;AlbumArt&lt;/a&gt; by using an Artist's Spotify URI or URL.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://d.pr/i/UlD4+" alt="Screenshot"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>LearningDiary: Rapid Prototyping</title><description>&lt;p&gt;This weekend, I took the time to build a service to keep track  of your learning. People today are not looking for another tool to solve their problems unless it solves a genuine problem but  rather want an added experience with their existing tools. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prototyping apps is becoming easier and&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>http://localhost:2368/2013/12/03/learningdiary-prototyping-apps-in-a-weekend-2/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">162d8912-94cb-4305-b75b-aaa49a429866</guid><category>Hack</category><dc:creator>Gaurav C</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 03 Dec 2013 15:51:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;This weekend, I took the time to build a service to keep track  of your learning. People today are not looking for another tool to solve their problems unless it solves a genuine problem but  rather want an added experience with their existing tools. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prototyping apps is becoming easier and simpler with the tools developers have access to today and I believe it is going to become shorter and shorter in the near future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Further, the best way you are learning is to actually be able to measure it. "If you can't measure it, it doesn't exist"&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, LearningDiary sends you an email everyday asking you what you learned today. As you log more learnings, it tracks what you wrote about recently and the next email has a snippet of what you learned from the past, a reference for you to know what to focus on next.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stack&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Node Express.JS 2. Mandrill SMTP as a service 3. Passport.js for Authentication 4. MongoHQ for for Users, Mails 5. Moment.js which is great to look at time/timezone manipulation in Javascript.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Give it a go. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://learningdiary.co/content/images/ld.png" alt="LearningDiary"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://learningdiary.co"&gt;LearningDiary&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Chrome Apps=Desktop Apps</title><description>&lt;p&gt;The new Chrome apps are versatile and remove the distinction between what a native desktop app can do vs what a web app can do. Chrome apps or Chrome extensions are written in HTML5, JS and CSS and are slowly being able to  access device resources like the USB, camera,&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>http://localhost:2368/2013/11/20/chrome-apps-desktop-apps-2/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">47cec7e6-c7c1-4146-8fed-7321b8194d45</guid><category>Chrome</category><dc:creator>Gaurav C</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 20 Nov 2013 01:15:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;The new Chrome apps are versatile and remove the distinction between what a native desktop app can do vs what a web app can do. Chrome apps or Chrome extensions are written in HTML5, JS and CSS and are slowly being able to  access device resources like the USB, camera, Graphics Processor, bare network utilities. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://developer.chrome.com/apps/samples.html"&gt;Chrome Samples&lt;/a&gt; gives a general idea of what Chrome apps can do. Further, Chrome apps are more accessible today than before. Before, Chrome apps could run in the background but could be initiated with a user action near the search bar on a small icon. Today, on a Mac, they land up in your docker. This was exciting because I personally wished that a few web services that I used existed as a dedicated desktop client app, like SoundCloud.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this context, I also have a favorite service of mine, &lt;a href="http://calm.com"&gt;Calm&lt;/a&gt; that I use often, but needed as a desktop app. With a simple manifest file and a webView tag in HTML, I was able to port it and I am loving the experience, albiet slighly  slower in performance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://f.cl.ly/items/2T3E2W1r300c3v0c3j2Q/calm.png" alt="Calm"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://chrome.google.com/webstore/detail/calm/cbgpebgejpbbmmhmdmhhenolmllkgdmi"&gt;Get it here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;div class="github-card" data-github="cggaurav/calm" data-width="400" data-height="177"&gt;&lt;/div&gt; &lt;script src="http://lab.lepture.com/github-cards/widget.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Symmetric Design | PaperJS</title><description>&lt;p&gt;I have been fascinated lately by symmetric design which have a heavy touch of  minimalism in them. I believe that to explore symmetry, we need to be able to see multiple perspectives of the design. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To start out, I took a Sandbox Logo and used Paper.js to animate it.&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>http://localhost:2368/2013/10/28/symmetric-design-paperjs-2/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">2a2ae846-8f3a-4c02-9eb3-56e03bd5d01f</guid><category>Design</category><dc:creator>Gaurav C</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 28 Oct 2013 22:54:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;I have been fascinated lately by symmetric design which have a heavy touch of  minimalism in them. I believe that to explore symmetry, we need to be able to see multiple perspectives of the design. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To start out, I took a Sandbox Logo and used Paper.js to animate it. All I needed to create the design was just a square, ie a square length and the angle of the parallellograms in them. Further, I rotate them to give you a feel of the symmetries that arise from such a simple thing. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This philosophy is in line with the examples that the Twitter logo can be constructed from sets of concentric circles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src="http://cggaurav.github.io/sandbox/" width="100%" heigth="800px"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Introducing Hood.ie</title><description>&lt;p&gt;I tried &lt;a href="http://hood.ie/#installation"&gt;Hood.ie&lt;/a&gt; today. Hoodie is a front end JS framework for you to quickly prototype web apps. Much like Meteor.JS but without &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; backend services that you have configure. They do have their own data-sync, user management and email backend services that you use out of the&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>http://localhost:2368/2013/10/21/introducing-hood-ie-2/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">fc68907d-e583-4193-8101-215c0b34f79f</guid><category>JS FW</category><category>Client</category><category>Hood.ie</category><dc:creator>Gaurav C</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 21 Oct 2013 21:07:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;I tried &lt;a href="http://hood.ie/#installation"&gt;Hood.ie&lt;/a&gt; today. Hoodie is a front end JS framework for you to quickly prototype web apps. Much like Meteor.JS but without &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; backend services that you have configure. They do have their own data-sync, user management and email backend services that you use out of the box via hoodie function call.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hood.ie thinks all data as user data, so they have a CouchDB instance to persist data for users. However, they have shared data for the public called global public shares and shared data between users called private user sharing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://f.cl.ly/items/373U1N1G1X0T1q1y3C0U/Screen%20Shot%202013-10-21%20at%2010.55.37%20PM.png" alt="Hoodie UI" title=""&gt; &lt;img src="http://f.cl.ly/items/0I2h1k3B38031L2X0l2z/Screen%20Shot%202013-10-21%20at%2010.57.26%20PM.png" alt="Hoodie Backend UI" title=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What will make Hood.ie usable is their plugins, which I hope it grows and ofcourse hosting on hood.ie itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://guide.couchdb.org/draft/security.html#authentication"&gt;CouchDB Cookie Authentication&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;em&gt;Off topic&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was curious as to how authenticated requests are made to CouchDB via jQuery. The requests should be  HTTPS request and I guess Hood.ie hosting should be configured with SSL.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A signup or login request is made to the CouchDB _session API via a POST request, the response of which has a Token that is valid for X minutes, which can be used for further authenticated requests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All passwords in CouchDB are salted.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>DigitalOcean, Docker and the changing World of DevOps</title><description>&lt;p&gt;Firstly, &lt;a href="https://www.digitalocean.com/pricing"&gt;DigitalOcean&lt;/a&gt; offers affordable cloud hosting with SSD and I immediately signed up for the $20 plan mostly to mess around with &lt;a href="https://www.docker.io/"&gt;Docker&lt;/a&gt; | As an alternative to EC2, this is bang for your buck.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enter Docker&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://f.cl.ly/items/3f16362q2y150D293s2J/Screen%20Shot%202013-10-11%20at%201.16.49%20PM.png" alt="Docker"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Docker is a Linux Container Engine and uses something called the AUFS – AnotherUnion File&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>http://localhost:2368/2013/10/11/digitalocean-docker-and-the-changing-world-of-devops/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">b2be4cf9-01d8-4ec3-8353-e82b75617ddf</guid><category>Digital Ocean</category><category>Docker</category><category>StackMachine</category><dc:creator>Gaurav C</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 11 Oct 2013 19:55:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Firstly, &lt;a href="https://www.digitalocean.com/pricing"&gt;DigitalOcean&lt;/a&gt; offers affordable cloud hosting with SSD and I immediately signed up for the $20 plan mostly to mess around with &lt;a href="https://www.docker.io/"&gt;Docker&lt;/a&gt; | As an alternative to EC2, this is bang for your buck.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enter Docker&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://f.cl.ly/items/3f16362q2y150D293s2J/Screen%20Shot%202013-10-11%20at%201.16.49%20PM.png" alt="Docker"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Docker is a Linux Container Engine and uses something called the AUFS – AnotherUnion File System.It is built solely for the purpose of sharing most of the OS resources which are critical and layers the changes needed for a backend service packaged as its own Docker Image. What this means is that you can have multiple docker content/images each running independantly on its own, relying on core OS utils and its dependencies are managed within its Docker container. Further, a docker image can be thought of as a git repository with a series of commits that can build and run, thereby making it easy to deploy changes and manage continous integration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Docker is still rough in the edges but I decided to run an elasticsearch server and a redis instance in production.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/cggaurav/docker-elasticsearch"&gt;Docker-Elasticsearch&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/cggaurav/docker-redis"&gt;Docker-Redis&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Things get tricky because you don’t have direct access to the docker image file system. Therefore, during run, you should share a mount folder where you can put a service’s configuration,data and logs. As per my convention, I have a DigitalOcean host directory /data/redis and /data/elasticsearch where I store each of the configuration,data and logs. That makes me backup data, change configuration( passwords, etc) and rerun the instance and clear logs with logrotate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks to &lt;a href="https://github.com/arcus-io/"&gt;Arcus-IO&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Further, the above content/images are public. For production you’ll need to bind public ports, have other custom config and not completely rely on docker run to pass time run time environment variables. I am not sure if this is a full blown problem to solve but &lt;a href="http://stackmachine.com"&gt;StackMachine&lt;/a&gt; came to the rescue – to be able to push and pull private docker content/images. The only thing I need to do in production is&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;docker pull stackmachine.com/rep docker run stackmachine.com/rep &amp;amp;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are tons of interesting content/images at &lt;a href="http://index.docker.io"&gt;Docker-Index&lt;/a&gt; and I am pretty excited to see what this becomes in a few months time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This is a highly brief post about the docker ecosystem in general. I     am writing individual posts on configuring services like logstash,     elasticsearch, redis in detail at a later point in time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content:encoded></item></channel></rss>